In this section, we'll
focus on tasks to process inputs, i.e.
the tasks that take the input and
generate a useful output, often through
a series of steps. It is
sometimes important for the model to
reason in detail about a problem
before answering a
specific question, and if
you took our previous course, ChatGPT Prompt
Engineering for Developers, you
will have seen a number of
examples of this. Sometimes a
model might make
reasoning errors by
rushing to an incorrect conclusion, so
we can reframe the query
to request a series
of relevant reasoning steps
before the model provides
a final answer, so that
it can think longer
and more methodically about
the problem.
And in general,
we call this strategy of
asking the model to reason
about a problem in steps,
"Chain of Thought Reasoning".
For some applications,
the reasoning process that
a model uses to arrive at a final
answer would be inappropriate
to share with the user. For example,
in tutoring applications,
we may want to
encourage students to work
on their own answers, but a model's
reasoning process about the student's solution
could reveal the answer
to the student.
Inner monologue is a
tactic that can be
used to mitigate this,
and this is just a fancy
way of saying hiding the model's
reasoning from the user.
The idea of inner
monologue is to instruct
the model to put
parts of the output
that are meant to
be hidden from the
user into a structured
format that makes passing them easy.
Then, before presenting the
output to the user,
the output is passed
and only part of the output is made
visible. So,
remember the classification problem
from a previous video,
where we asked the
model to classify a
customer query into a
primary and secondary category.
And based on that classification,
we might want to take different
instructions. Imagine the customer
query had been classified into the
product information category.
In the next instructions, we'll
want to include
information about the
products we have available.
And so, in this case,
the classification would
have been primary, general inquiry,
secondary, product information.
And so, let's dive into an example
starting from there.
So, let's
start with our usual setup.
So, for this inner monologue example,
we'll start with our same
delimiters that we've been
using.
And now, let's
go through our system message.
And so, what we're doing here is asking
the model to reason
about the answer before
coming to its conclusion. So, the
instruction is, "Follow
these steps to answer
the customer queries. The
customer query will be
delimited with four hashtags.", our
delimiter.
So, then we've
split this up into steps.
So, the first step is to
"Decide whether the user is asking
a question about a specific product
or products.
And a product category doesn't
count.".
Step two, so, "If the user is
asking about specific products,
identify whether the products
are in the following list.".
And now we've included a list
of available products. So, here
we have five available products.
They're all varieties of laptops
and these are all
made up products. They
were actually generated by GPT-4.
And step three,
"If the message contains
products in the list above,
list any assumptions that the user
is making in their message.
For example,
that laptop X is bigger
than laptop Y or that
laptop Z has a 2 year warranty."
for example.
Step four is,
"If the user made any assumptions,
figure out whether the
assumption is true based
on your product information.".
And step five is, "First,
politely correct the customer's
incorrect assumptions, if
applicable. Only
mention or reference products
in the list of
5 available products, as
these are the only five
products that the store sells. And
answer the customer in
a friendly tone."
And these kind of very pedantic
instructions are probably
unnecessary for a
more advanced language
model like GPT-4.
And then we'll ask the model to
use the following format.
So, step one, delimiter, it's
reasoning. Step two, delimiter, reasoning
and so on.
And using the delimiters
will mean that it
will be easier for us later to get
just this response to the customer.
And kind of cut off everything before.
So, now let's
try an example user message.
So, our message is, "by how much is
the BlueWave Chromebook more
expensive than the TechPro desktop?"
So, let's
take a look at these two products.
The BlueWave Chromebook is 249.99.
And the TechPro desktop is actually 999.99.
This is not actually true.
And so, let's see how the model
handles this user request.
So, we'll
format into our messages array. And
we'll get our response.
And then we'll print it.
And so what we're hoping for is
that the model takes all of
these different steps
and realises that the user has
made an incorrect assumption
and then follows the final step
to politely correct the user.
And so, within this one prompt we've
actually maintained a number of different
complex states that
the system could be in. So, you
know, at any given point
there could be a different output
from the previous step and we
would want to do something different.
For example, if
the user hadn't made
any assumptions in step 3, then in
step 4 we wouldn't actually have
any output. So this is
a pretty complicated instruction for
the model. So let's see
if it did it right. So step 1, the
user is asking a question about specific
products. They're asking about the
price difference between these
two products.
The user assumes that the BlueWave
Chromebook is more
expensive than the TechBook Pro and
this assumption is
actually incorrect.
It's reasoning through, taking
longer to think about the problem.
In the same way that
a human would also
take some time to
reason about an answer
to any given question, the
model performs better if it
also has time to think.
And so the final
response to the user
is the BlueWave Chromebook
is actually less expensive
than the TechBook Pro.
The TechBook Pro desktop costs $999.99,
while
the BlueWave Chromebook costs $249.99.
And so let's
see another example of a user message.
And also at this point,
feel free to pause the
video and try your own messages.
So let's format this user message. So
the question is, "do
you sell TVs?". And if you remember in
our product list, we've only
listed different computers. So let's
see what the model says.
So in this case, step one,
the user is asking
if the store sells TVs,
but TVs are not
listed in the available products.
So as you can see, the model then
skips to the response to user
step because it realizes that the
intermediary steps are
not actually necessary.
I will say that we did ask for
the output in this specific format.
So technically, the model hasn't
exactly followed our request.
Again, more advanced models will
be better at doing that.
And so in this case,
our response to the user is, "I'm
sorry, but
we do not sell TVs at the store."
And then it lists the available
products.
So again, feel free to try
some of your own responses.
And so now, we only really want
this part of the response.
We wouldn't want to show the earlier
parts to the user. So
what we can do is actually just cut
the string at the
last occurrence of this
delimiter token or string
of four hashtags and
then only print the
final part of the model output.
So let's write some code to get only
the final part of this string. So
we're going
to use a try except block.
To gracefully handle errors
in case the model has some kind of
unpredictable output and doesn't
actually use these characters.
And so we're going to say our
final response is the
response and then we're going
to split the string at
the delimiter string.
And because we want the final
occurrence, we just want to get the
last item in the output list.
And then we're
going to strip any white space.
Because as you can see,
there might be white
space after the characters.
Then we're going to catch any
errors and have a
fallback response which is, "Sorry,
I'm having trouble right now. Please try
asking another question.". And then
let's print our
final response.
And so as you can see,
we just cut the string
to get this final output.
And so this is what we would show
to the user if
we were building this
into an application.
And overall, I just want to call
out this prompt might be
slightly convoluted for this task.
You might not actually need all
of these intermediate steps.
And so why don't you try and see if
you can find an easier
way to do the same
task in your own prompt.
And in general,
finding the optimal trade-off
in prompt complexity
requires some experimentation.
So definitely good to try a
number of different
prompts before deciding to use one.
And in the next video, we'll
learn another strategy to handle complex
tasks by splitting
these complex tasks
into a series of simpler subtasks
rather than trying to do the
whole task in one prompt.